Hello everyone and welcome to
English Pod, my name is Markle.
My name is Katherine and we're talking
today about health and getting sick.
That's right, we are going to visit the
doctor so we're feeling a little bit ill and
what we're going to
describe some of the
symptoms that we have and the doctor
is going to recommend some medicine.
Alright, so let's take a
listen to today's dialogue and
we'll be back in a moment
to talk about what's going on.
Good afternoon Chloe, I'm Dr. Evans,
what seems to be the problem?
Hi Dr. Evans, thanks for
seeing me on such short notice.
When I woke up this morning I had a
really sore throat and a really bad cough.
I think I'm coming down with the flu.
Ah, I see, yes you do sound rather croaky.
Well let's have a look shall we, could
you please open your mouth and say ah?
Good, yes, your tonsils
are a little swollen
and red, how are your
ears blocked at all?
A little actually, my sinuses are a little
blocked up as well, I really feel terrible.
Okay Chloe can you
please breathe in and out
slowly for me while I
listen to your chest?
Wow you really are all bunged
up, you don't sound too good at
all, okay I'm going to set you
up with a bunch of antibiotics.
You will need to take
these orange pills twice
a day and these blue
pills every evening.
You will also have to take this cough
medicine three times a day after meals.
Finally, I am giving
you an inhaler to use
every time you feel breathless
just to clear up your lungs.
Whoa, so many drugs, ah, I hate
swallowing pills, am I able to go to work?
Absolutely not, you're highly contagious.
You don't want to infect the
rest of your co-workers do you?
I recommend staying
in bed for at least three
days and drinking plenty of fluids so
you don't get weak and dehydrated.
You can catch up on all the
latest TV shows and movies.
Okay, would you mind writing
me a doctor's note for work?
Otherwise they may think I'm faking it.
Sure, no problem.
Here you are.
Now, off home in a
way to bed, if you have
any questions just give me a
call, feel better soon and take care.
Thanks, Doc.
Bye.
All right, we're back so now
let's take a look at six key
words that we have prepared for
you today on language takeaway.
So oftentimes in the
wintertime when the air
is very, very dry and maybe
you have a cold, you get this.
This is the first thing
we're talking about.
That's right.
We have a sore throat.
Okay, so Chloe in the
dialogue says I woke up
this morning and I
had a really sore throat.
Right.
So let's take a look at those two words.
We know throat is the
part of your neck, right?
Connects your head to your body.
That's right.
And the word sore.
That means it hurts.
So I could have a sore
back or sore knees,
sore is basically an
adjective that describes pain.
Pain.
So you have an ache in your throat.
All right, so that's a sore throat.
And well, she said
that she has this sore
throat and the doctor says, I seen,
yes, you do sound rather crochee.
Okay, crochee is a way
to describe the way a
person sounds, especially
when they're talking
and maybe their voice I
think is very deep or rough.
Right.
So usually if you have
a sore throat or a very
bad cough, you sound
a little bit crochee.
So you're like, hey,
my throat, or it's a
little bit exactly not a
very nice way to sound.
It comes from the way
that frogs croak, right?
Yeah, that's the sound that frogs make.
They croak.
So yeah, sometimes when you
do have a sore throat or a very bad
cough, people say that you
have a frog in your throat, right?
All right, so that's the word crochee.
Now, moving on, if
you have a sore throat,
it's usually because
your tonsils are swollen.
Okay, so the first word here,
tonsils, these are a body part.
They're in your throat,
the very back of your
throat, and you usually
have two of them.
Some people don't have any though.
Right, some people get them removed.
They're like little balls
in the back of your throat.
And I don't really know what they do.
I think they pick up some, I
don't know what they do really.
So thank you, need them, actually.
Because a lot of people have them taken out
when they're young, but tonsils when they
are infected or when they are
swollen are very, very painful.
You can have really bad sore throats.
Right, and usually they can
cause fevers and stuff like that.
So some people get them removed.
And well, as we said,
your tonsils are swollen.
So if they are swollen,
that means they are big.
That's right.
So swollen means
they're bigger than normal.
And you can say this
about many different things.
For example, maybe
someone stepped on my toe,
and my toe really hurts, and I
looked down, and it's swollen.
That means my toe got bigger.
Okay, so this is an
adjective when something
is swollen, but the verb form
to say that something swells.
Right?
It gets bigger.
It gets bigger to swell.
Or the adjective, it is swollen.
All right, and now she
was talking a little bit about
her sinuses, that her
sinuses are a little blocked up.
So sinuses are in your face.
You have them in your
nose, and under your eyes.
And when they hurt,
it's actually quite painful.
And people say that sometimes their sinuses
are aggravated, or they have bad sinuses.
This means they're having
a hard time breathing,
or their faces sore,
their eyes are sore.
That's very common.
Okay.
So that's sinuses.
Actually, a condition
that if you have blocked
sinuses all the time,
they call it sinusitis.
Sinusitis.
Yeah, so that's a problem that
comes back again and again.
Okay.
And the doctor also recommended her
to rest because she is highly contagious.
Okay, so you want to stay away
from people who are contagious.
This means that what
disease they have, or what
illness they have, can
affect other people.
So if I have the flu Marko and I
come to work, it's pretty contagious.
It's very likely that you will get the flu.
That's right.
So a flu is very highly contagious, or
many other things are highly contagious.
For example, pink eye is very contagious,
but you know, cancer is not contagious.
That's right.
If you have cancer, I can't
get it from touching you.
Right.
Very good.
So contagious.
All right.
Why don't we go back
and listen to our dialogue
again, and we'll be back in a little
bit to talk about fluency builder.
Good afternoon, Chloe.
I'm Dr. Evans.
What seems to be the problem?
Hi, Dr. Evans.
Thanks for seeing me on such short notice.
When I woke up this morning, I had a
really sore throat and a really bad cough.
I think I'm coming down with the flu.
Ah, I see.
Yes, you do sound rather croaky.
Well, let's have a look, shall we?
Would you please open
your mouth and say, ah?
Ah, good, yes.
Your tonsils are a little swollen and red.
How are your ears blocked at all?
A little, actually.
My sinuses are a little blocked up as well.
I really feel terrible.
OK, Chloe, can you
please breathe in and out
slowly for me while I
listen to your chest?
[LAUGHS]
Wow, you really are all bunged up.
You don't sound too good at all.
OK, I'm going to set you
up with a bunch of antibiotics.
You will need to take
these orange pills twice
a day and these blue
pills every evening.
You will also have to take this cough
medicine three times a day after meals.
Finally, I'm giving
you an inhaler to use
every time you feel breathless,
just to clear up your lungs.
Whoa, so many drugs.
Ah, I hate swallowing pills.
Am I able to go to work?
Absolutely not.
You're highly contagious.
You don't want to infect the
rest of your co-workers, do you?
I recommend staying
in bed for at least three
days and drinking plenty of fluids so
you don't get weak and dehydrated.
You can catch up on all the
latest TV shows and movies.
OK, would you mind writing
me a doctor's note for work?
Otherwise they may think I'm faking it.
[LAUGHS]
Sure, no problem.
Here you are.
Now, off home in a way to bed.
If you have any questions,
just give me a call.
Feel better soon and take care.
Thanks, Doc.
Bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right, we're back.
So now let's take a
look at four key phrases
that we have prepared
for you on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So Chloe goes in
to see her doctor, Dr.
Evans, and she says, thanks for
seeing me on such short notice.
What's short notice?
All right, so basically,
Chloe made an
appointment with the doctor
very late or very suddenly.
Right?
So that's a short notice.
Great.
So for example, it's
Friday night, and she needs
to make an appointment
for Saturday morning.
That's pretty short notice.
That's not calling the doctor in advance.
You can say this also when
you're talking to friends.
Mm-hmm.
I'm really sorry to cancel on such short
notice, but I can't go to dinner tonight.
Right.
So I think it's very
interesting, the whole
structure, as you see,
on such short notice.
So as you said, your example.
I'm really sorry to cancel
on such short notice.
On short notice, on such short notice.
Mm-hmm.
That's right.
All right.
So moving on to her
second phrase, Chloe was
explaining that she
doesn't feel very well.
And she said, I think I'm
coming down with the flu.
Okay.
So let's look at this verbal
phrase here, coming down with.
Okay.
So you can come down
with many different illnesses.
But the verb here means, this
is the beginning of my illness.
So I'm starting to feel the effects.
Like you said, Marco, I'm
feeling some symptoms.
So I'm starting to get sick, right?
I'm coming down with a fever.
Mm-hmm.
Or I think I'm coming down with a cold.
Very common.
All right.
And the doctor started to check,
Chloe, how she was breathing.
I think he listened to her lungs
with his, what is it called, the fiscope.
Stethoscope.
And he said, wow, you
are really all bunged up.
All right.
So here, he's basically saying
that she's very congested.
That means that her
breathing passageways,
like in her nose and her throat
and her chest, are very stuffy.
There's things in them.
Right.
Usually mucus, phlem, phlem.
These are things
that, you know, it's in
your nose and you have a
cold and you have to blow it out.
That's phlem and mucus.
Yeah, not a very pretty thing.
No.
Very disgusting, actually.
So maybe we should
move on to our next item.
All right.
So she's all bunged up and a clear up.
And so he recommended
a couple of different
medicine, such as
antibiotics, some pills, and
he also gave her an
inhaler to clear up her lungs.
Okay.
So an inhaler is
basically a device that you
use to put steroids in your
lungs that will help you breathe.
So some people,
when they're running or
they're walking, they're
very short of breath.
And they can't breathe.
Well, there's a problem
with this, like asthma
and they need to
breathe this little inhaler.
Right.
And it's like a little tube.
I think it's you inhaled
medicine from this little tube.
Yeah.
And it helps open up your passageways.
It helps you breathe.
And it's very important for some people.
But in the case of an
illness, like your lungs
are very congested, this helps
you breathe on the short term.
Right.
So basically, clear up is to
allow air or the movement
of something within
your body usually, I think.
Right.
But to clear up isn't
necessarily about air,
it's basically a way
to say that it will
make this problem go away, to clear
something up is to make the problem go.
Right.
So I guess if you get
medicine from a doctor,
he'll say, okay, this will
help you clear up your throat.
Right.
Or if you have a
problem with acne, maybe
your doctor will give
you some cream to help
clear up your acne, make it
go away clear up your skin.
Okay.
So a lot of great examples there, why don't
we go back and listen to the dialogue one
last time.
Good afternoon, Chloe.
I'm Dr. Evans.
It seems to be the problem.
Hi, Dr. Evans.
Thanks for seeing me on such short notice.
When I woke up this morning, I had a
really sore throat and a really bad cough.
I think I'm coming down with the flu.
Ah, I see.
Yes, you do sound rather croaky.
Well, let's have a look, shall we?
Could you please open
your mouth and say, ah?
Ah, good, yes.
Your tonsils are a little swollen and red.
How are your ears blocked at all?
A little, actually.
My sinuses are a little blocked up as well.
I really feel terrible.
Okay, Chloe, can you
please breathe in and out
slowly for me while I
listen to your chest?
Wow, you really are all bunged up.
You don't sound too good at all.
Okay, I'm going to set you
up with a bunch of antibiotics.
You will need to take
these orange pills twice
a day and these blue
pills every evening.
You will also have to take this cough
medicine three times a day after meals.
Finally, I'm giving
you an inhaler to use
every time you feel breathless,
just to clear up your lungs.
Whoa, so many drugs.
Ah, I hate swallowing pills.
Am I able to go to work?
Absolutely not.
You're highly contagious.
You don't want to infect the
rest of your co-workers, do you?
I recommend staying
in bed for at least three
days and drinking plenty of fluids so
you don't get weak and dehydrated.
You can catch up on all the
latest TV shows and movies.
Okay, would you mind writing
me a doctor's note for work?
Otherwise they may think I'm faking it.
Sure, no problem.
Here you are.
Now, off home in a way to bed.
If you have any questions,
just give me a call.
Feel better soon and take care.
Thanks, Doc.
Bye.
Alright, so talking
about illnesses and being
contagious, we mentioned
this pink eye illness before.
So this is the
colloquial way of saying
conjunctivitis, which is I don't
know if anyone has ever gotten it.
Your eye gets very, very red
for a prolonged period of time.
That's right.
Itches a lot.
Itches.
Already, your eye is
very red or pink, like
the name says, but you really want
to scratch it and it's really hard not to.
Yeah.
And I think you treated by
means of some eye drops.
Yeah.
And you have to wait.
I actually had a very
bad case of pink eye
once that I couldn't
just clear up with drops.
But the doctor gave me some eye drops.
They were so strong that I put
them in my eye and I can taste them.
Oh wow.
Yeah.
But apparently it's very
strange and it wouldn't clear up.
So then I had to get
some kind of like a
clear gel put in my eye and my
eye patched up for like two days.
Oh wow.
Yeah.
So I was running around with one eye.
It was crazy.
Well, I've never had
it, but I know that it's
very, very contagious,
like we were saying earlier.
And so if a student
at a school gets pink
eye, all the parents get
very nervous because
it's very, very likely that he or
she will give it to another person.
Yeah.
If you touch your eye
and you touch someone
else, all of a sudden,
they have this disease.
Exactly.
So yeah, it's very common thing.
And I think with, especially with kids,
they always get all these things, pink eye,
measles, they get chicken pox,
chicken pox, a lot of different disease.
We actually have a lesson on chicken pox.
You guys should check that one out.
But if you have any
questions, any comments or
any other doubts, please
come to EnglishPod.
com or we're there
to answer them.
We'll see you there.
Bye.
[MUSIC]